Finding Aid for James M. Plumer papers, 1921-1958
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James M. Plumer papers 1921-1958
Plumer, James Marshall, 1899-1960.
2 linear feet
85328 Aa 2
Civil servant with Chinese Maritime Customs Service, later professor of Far Eastern art at the University of Michigan. Letters to his mother describing his experiences in China, other related papers, and photographs from his years in China.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in several accessions in 1980, 1981, and 1986, by Carol Plumer (donor no. 6463 ), the widow of James M. Plumer.
The collection is open to research.
James Marshall Plumer was born on July 10, 1899, at Newton Centre, Massachusetts. He graduated from Harvard University (B.A., 1921; M.A., 1937). From 1923 to 1937, he served in China as a member of the staff of the Chinese Maritime Customs Service. On periodic leaves, Plumer also held an appointment as assistant and tutor in Chinese language at Harvard. He also served as secretary of the Harvard-Yenching Institute, 1929-1930. In 1935, during another leave, Plumer was appointed lecturer on Far Eastern Art at the University of Michigan, where he taught for twenty-five years, eventually holding the rank of Professor of Far Eastern Art.
Plumer contributed numerous articles to scholarly journals in the field of Far Eastern Art, and was editor (1952-1958) of the Far Eastern Ceramic Bulletin. He also completed and edited Langdon Warner's book, Japanese Sculpture of the Tempyo Period.
James Plumer died June 15, 1960.
The Plumer collection has been arranged into the following series: Letters to his mother from China; Other Materials; and Photographs. The letters to his mother are bound together in seven volumes with occasional descriptive photographs. The letters describe his experiences in Nanking, Manchuria, Shanghai, and Hankow, and his vacation trip to India in 1928. Also included are typescripts of selective letters. The Photographs series consists of people, buildings, and views in China, especially in Nanking and Manchuria. There are also photos of visits to Hong Kong, India, Japan, and the Philippines.
Subjects:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China. Hai guan zong shui wu si shu.; India.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Plumer, James Marshall.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China. Hai guan zong shui wu si shu.; Hong Kong (China); India.; Japan.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Plummer family.; Shipping.; Ships.; Tourism.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.
- Letters to his mother (bound)
  (include photographs)
  - April 1923-June 1924 Nanking (Box 1)
  - June-October 1924 Nanking (Box 1)
  - October 1924-October 1925 Moukden, Manchuria (Box 1)
  - October 1925-February 1926 Shanghai (Box 1)
  - April 1926-January 1927 Shanghai (Box 1)
  - January 1927-April 1928 Hankow (Box 1)
  - April-July 1928 India vacation (Box 1)
  - Typescripts of letters (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Personal and biographical (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1948-1949, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Citation and award from Japan (Box 1)
  - Chinese business cards (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Programs, notices of speeches, etc. (Box 1)
  - Trip to Nara, Japan, for dedication of Langdon Warner memorial (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Temmoku, A Study of the Ware of Chien (typescript) (Box 1)
  - China Maritime Customs Service List, 1921, 1934-1937, 5 volumes (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Chinese provinces, cities, and sites
    - Chao Chow
      (includes Nanking)
      - 1923 (Box 2)
      - 1924 (Box 2)
      - 1926-1928 undated (Box 2)
    - Hua Shan, negatives (Box 2)
    - Hui Chow trip (Box 2)
    - Kaifeng (Box 2)
    - Kalgan (Box 2)
    - Kia Tung (Kiating) (Box 2)
    - Kwei Hwa (Kweihwa) (Box 2)
    - Liang lions and Hsi Hsia Shan (Box 2)
    - Liang lions (photos by J.F. Russell) (Box 2)
    - Long Old Road, photos and negatives (Box 2)
    - Loyang, negatives (Box 2)
    - Lung men, negatives (Box 2)
    - Shensi and Kansu, Buddhist caves, negatives (Box 2)
    - Shu Shan and Kading, negatives (Box 2)
    - Sian (Box 2)
    - Tatung (Box 2)
    - T'ung Kuan, negatives (Box 2)
    - Wu Ch'iang, negatives (Box 2)
    - Wu-hu (Box 2)
    - Yangtze (Kuling, Anking), negatives (Box 2)
    - Yangtze River (Box 2)
    - Yun Kang, 1 folders; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Personal photos (Plumer family) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Art works (Box 2)
    - Japan (Box 2)
    - Unidentified (Box 2)
    - Negatives (Box 2)
  - Albums
    - Foochow 1932-1933 (Box 2)
      (negatives with index)
    - Nanking, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Manchuria (Box 2)
    - Wu-Han (Box 2)
    - World tour as merchant seaman 1921-1922 (Box 2)
      (includes photos of Japan, China, and Philippines)
    - Unidentified, 2 volumes (Box 2)